Boker tov בוקר טוב *Boker tov* everybody.
I could eat meat, I could eat meat. Okay, boker tov בוקר
טוב *Boker tov*, today is Bava Batra Kuf Nun Vav בבא בתרא
קנ"ו *Bava Batra Kuf Nun Vav* 156. We pick up at the
bottom of Kuf Nun He Amud Bet קנ"ה עמוד ב' *Kuf Nun
He Amud Bet*. We're in the middle of a discussion
which the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* got to as a bit of
a digression but that's the famous story in the question about if
somebody has a shtar שטר *Shtar* and then there's a claim about
something that makes the shtar שטר *Shtar* effectively void. Our Mishnah משנה
mishnah. *Mishnah* was the issue that the person titled the shtar שטר
*Shtar* Shuchmis Ra שכיב מרע Shichiv Meyra. *Shuchmis Ra*. The Gemara גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* dealt with cases about somebody who sold land and then
the brother he died and the brother said he actually was a
katan קטן katan, *Katan*, was underage. And the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says it's not just a katan קטן katan. *Katan* in the sense
of being under Bar Mitzvah בר bar מצוה mitzvah *Bar Mitzvah*, but
there's actually a principle that to sell property and as the Gemara
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is about to clarify here to sell land in
one's father's estate, one has to be either 18 or 20.
A katan gadol קטן גדול *Katan gadol*.
Exactly. So and then the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* made distinctions that
maybe even if he is 20, if he's particularly irresponsible it doesn't
work, even if he's under 20, if he's particularly savvy in the
ways of business it does work. Okay but those were the various
issues. So now the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* picks up and says
the following.
So if he's irresponsible and he's 30, it would still work anyway?
No, it would not. Mean it doesn't seem like there's no it's
not clear like where the cutoff line is. Okay but that is
something which is much more contextual. Meaning there is the quantifiable issue
of 20 or whatever, but then there's these big categories of possible
exceptions.
So the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't make it clear if there
would be a cutoff line. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
like this. All right, so we discussed that yesterday. So I mean
let's read a little bit here in the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara*,
we'll discuss it again. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like
this. Amar Rav Huna Beray De'rav Yehoshua אמר רב הונא Rav Huna
בריה דרב יהושע *Amar Rav Huna Beray De'rav Yehoshua*, it is six
lines from the bottom on Kuf Nun He Amud Bet קנ"ה עמוד
ב' *Kuf Nun He Amud Bet*. Says Rav Huna the son of
Rav Yehoshua, u'le'edut eduto edut ולאדות עדותו עדות edus *U'le'edut eduto edut*.
This guy, guy who's under 20, even though he can't sell his
land in his father's property, he can testify on a transaction that
took place that involved land. And as we said the point being
like it's not like he's completely clueless and he doesn't understand what's
going on. He is intelligent, okay? It's just we don't trust his
judgment like to actually decide it's worth it for him to sell
the land and again the reason to go back to things we
said yesterday why land is particularly important. You know land sort of
represents the fundamental inheritance, the patrimony, like that's you know the classic
yerusha ירושה *Yerusha* and so on. So the idea is that we
want to protect the person from squandering this or protect the family
from this being squandered and lost. You know again maybe also this
was particularly at a time when you were no longer dealing with
a Yovel יובל *Yovel*. So stuff that was sold wasn't going to
come back you know in any way. So therefore you know you
really wanted and the other point I also made and was made
by the Rashbam רשב"ם Rashbam, *Rashbam* and Tosafot תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* as
well that this only applies to land that's inherited, not necessarily to
land that the person like earns and purchases and so on on
their own because in one way again to explain that is it's
not the father's estate so it's not that idea of that sense
of like continuity with the previous generations, you know the sort of
identity of the family. But another point also is you know people
easy come easy go. Somebody gets something through an inheritance they might
not be as responsible and appreciate as much you know what it
means to really you know own it and possess it. So for
all these various reasons we're afraid that their judgment is going to
be you know immature. They're under 20. But they certainly are kosher
le'edut כשר לעדות *Kosher le'edut* fundamentally and aware enough you know intelligent
enough to interpret what's going on. So it is a legitimate they
are legitimate as edut עדות edus *Edut*. Amar Mar Zutra אמר מר
זוטרא Mar Zutra *Amar Mar Zutra*, lo amran ela le'metaltelin לא אמרן
אלא Ella, למטלטלין *Lo Amran Ela Le'metaltelin*. That's only for metaltelin מטלטלין
metaltelin. *Metaltelin* and he actually pushes that. Aval le'karkei lo אבל לקרקעי
לא *Aval le'karkei lo*, not for karkei קרקעי *Karkei*. The same way
that they can't sell land and here it's implicit this distinction of
karkei קרקעי *Karkei* and metaltelin מטלטלין metaltelin? *Metaltelin*, it really was not
said even implicitly before and it's not even said explicitly here. But
okay but for land since he can't sell it presumably he can't
be an ed עד *Ed*, but metaltelin מטלטלין metaltelin *Metaltelin* he can.
Maybe he assumes the same reason we don't trust you to do
a sale we don't trust your ability to
he's just reporting the facts.
I understand that's the distinction I made between intelligence and judgment, but
he feels like you can't always clearly draw that line. Amar lay
Rav Ashi l'Mar Zutra אמר ליה Amar Lei, רב Rav אשי למר
זוטרא *Amar lay Rav Ashi l'Mar Zutra*, mai shena metaltelin de'zvineh zvini
מאי שנא מטלטלין metaltelin, דזביניה זביני *Mai shena metaltelin de'zvineh zvini*. And
here the Gemara גמרא Gemara *Gemara* makes it clear. Right, metaltelin מטלטלין
metaltelin *Metaltelin* presumably you assume he could be a good ed עד
*Ed* because if he sells it's good, so therefore he could be
a good ed עד *Ed*. Okay. Ela me'ata אלא מעתה *Ela me'ata*
and therefore but karkei קרקעי *Karkei* you assume since the sale won't
be good the edut עדות edus. *Edut* won't be good. So he
says ela me'ata אלא מעתה *Ela me'ata* if you say that, hadetnan
הא דתנן *Hadetnan* hapi'utot mekachan mekach u'memkaran memkar be'metaltelin הפעוטות מקחן מקח
וממכרן ממכר במטלטלין *Hapi'utot mekachan mekach u'memkaran memkar be'metaltelin*. Pi'utot פעוטות *Pi'utot*
which are like small kids, like about six or seven years old,
Chazal חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* allowed them to actually engage in transactions for
metaltelin מטלטלין Metaltelin *Metaltelin*, like you know when they go to a
store to buy a gallon of milk, you can't say ah I
can't sell to you because it won't be a legal transaction, you
have to send your father here or something like that. So they
actually allowed actually said that because so much of just daily living
requires the buying and selling of מטלטלין, Metaltelin they actually allowed it
to be valid for these young kids. Now the funny thing is
is that like, you know, okay, that's like a gallon of milk,
but you're what, like a seven-year-old is going to be able to
sell you like this this this diamond, you know, which is like
you know for a million dollars, you know, let's say they happen
to have inherited a lot of money, like what are the limits,
you know, on that? That's not clear. But anyway, but the point
is רב הונא Rav Huna. although you normally need to be בר
בת bat מצווה mitzvah did allow for for these young kids to
do these transactions of מטלטלין. Metaltelin So he's saying if for you
it tracks with if you can be an עדות edus when you
can do a good sale, so maybe we should let a six
or seven-year-old be an עדות edus. for issues of מטלטלין?
Categorically excluded from עדות.
edus All right. So anyway, well that's going to be the point.
The point is going to be that there are two criteria. So
he says הכי נמי דעדות עדות, hachi nami de'edus edus, what you
think their עדות edus? would be good? אמר ליה התם בעינן ועמדו
שני האנשים דליכא. amar lei hatam beinan ve'amdu shenei ha'anashim de'leika. No,
no, no. There are two criteria. There's a formal criteria that you
have to be an adult and as Michael says you have to
be a man. Okay, and but just because you satisfy that formal
criteria doesn't mean that in like that there might not be additional
criteria that we put on you. Okay, so it's not enough that
your sale is valid. It has to both be the adult and
male adult that is required by הלכה halacha and somebody who, like
in these cases of business or whatever, is of the age that
we would actually recognize your sales as being valid, your transactions as
being valid, because you need that degree of understanding and judgment to
be a good עדות. edus So you need both. You need both
the formal age and sex and you need, you know, the degree
of judgment. So he is saying that you have to to be
an עדות edus, you have to be an adult and you have
to be for issues of מטלטלין you can be בר מצווה bar
mitzvah and for issues of קרקע karka you would have to be
twenty. You would need both combined. Okay, but here it is also
implicit that the limits on sale בנכסי אביו benichsei aviv apply specifically
to קרקע. karka. Now תוספות Tosafot does not understand this to be
what we've just said, that it's just a question about like I'm
saying oh yeah like you know Michael bought a plot of land
from you know from Eli etc. etc. So you look at תוספות
Tosafot and he understands that the reason to limit the age might
be because something that requires even more judgment or more whatever discernment.
He says לא אמרו אלא מטלטלי אבל קרקעי לא lo amru ela
metalteli aval karkei lo אין לפרש לעדות קרקע ein laparesh le'edus karka
דמאי שנא למטלטלין. demai shna lemetaltelin. Okay, תוספות Tosafot says I don't
get it, big deal, if you can't sell, why does it mean
you can't be an
עדות? Edut. ועוד דהכא לא שייך שום שטות, ve'od dehacha lo shayach
shum shtus, like which is
you know again this what sort of argument that I was making
for רב הונא. Rav Huna, It might be that there's a judgment
concern, but why does that mean in terms of doing whether you're
trusted to do your own transactions, why does that mean you can't
testify in terms of what occurred? Okay, so again that's my understanding
of רב Rav הונא, but he's trying to understand מר זוטרא Mar
Zutra that says you can't be an עדות eidut, for קרקע. karka.
So he says אלא נראה לפרש היינו עדות שיאמרו כך וכך היתה
שוה זו הקרקע. ela nireh laparesh hainu edus sheyomru kach vekach hayta
shava zo hakarka. Okay, that you're actually testifying that sold land and
it was worth X amount, but he charged such amount. So now
you that's real...
Why would you need to testify how much it was worth? Because
sometimes yeah... what, as an estimator?
Well yeah, because sometimes there is like you know, I mean although
it's true that like אין אונאה בקרקעות, ein ona'ah bekarka'ot, there are
times in which there you know in which there can be issues
of אונאה ona'ah and overcharging.
Okay, so like more than 100%?
Yeah, whatever the case might be. I don't want to go into
it. But yes. Okay, so but the point is of course if
that's true, you know, then the question is wouldn't it only require
to be twenty? I would think that that would be a specialty,
right? I bet nobody here would be trust... I wouldn't trust anybody
here to assess what a piece of land was worth. So anyway,
okay. דכיון דמקרבא דעתיה לגבי זוזי וימכרוהו ביותר משויו, dekeivan demikarva da'ateih
legabei zuzei veyimkeruhu beyoter mishavyo, he's now alluding to what we're going
to say, it ties into the judgment issue. The same way he
might make a bad judgment and say, you know what, I'll give
you a thousand dollars for this lit... little piece of land, right?
So you know, your... so if you're young you might not appreciate
a little piece of land is worth as opposed to a thousand
dollars is very tempting. So we're going to say in a minute
right that that's why we we don't allow the sale to be
good, because you're not you don't trust your judgment and you're too
seduced by like the money and you don't appreciate the value of
the land. So תוספות Tosafot wants to tie it in. So it's
all about being seduced by hearing a dollar value and not appreciating
the value of the land. So that's why you're not trusted to
assess what the dollar value is. תוספות Tosafot wants to make it
all the same type of a logic and tie it directly into
why we're going to say in a minute that the sale is
not valid. But again, the real point is that most people, I
mean maybe if you live in an agrarian society and you know
everybody knows what a standard acre of a good farmland is worth,
you know, maybe it is something that isn't as much of a
specialty as it is today. But nevertheless, like that's the way תוספות
Tosafot limits it. Yes, רב דב. Rabbi Dov.
Wait, when you were talking about the formal definition of עדות, edut,
are you referencing the רשב"א? Rashba? The תוספות Tosafot he seems to
think means...
Yeah, I said boys and girls. Yeah, but that was a special
Rabbinic תקנה. Takkanah. Right. That's about transactions; that's not about עדות.
Yeah, but transactions, can one abstract from like a broader case if
they don't have a degree in psychology it can't be trusted whether
that person is a שוטה Shoteh or whatever it is.
Yeah, you know I mean look, even in American law the whole
question about expert testimony, I mean I forget I read about it
once, you know it's not so פשוט, pashut, right? Because it's not
something that the court can directly assess. Like, it's not like normal
testimony that you're telling facts and the court is assessing what it
means, but you're sort of trusting somebody's assessment of that fact, right?
So like how that even functioned in like secular law was like
a חידוש chiddush about how much they can use like expert testimony.
So I don't know, like in הלכה Halacha you normally don't have
that concept. I'd have to think more about it. Right, but here
we're... No, תוספות Tosafot, isn't making it. תוספות, Tosafot I mean we
were sort of saying, we were saying like I don't know if
I would trust a normal person to assess it, but תוספות Tosafot
is actually saying no, a normal person can, it's just somebody who's
under the age of twenty whose judgment isn't you know good enough.
Meaning not you don't need to be an expert you just need
to have a certain maturity of judgment, right?
So how do we get twenty?
The גמרא Gemara never said. It was just, I mean we were
in שיעור Shiur we discussed obviously the idea that twenty is an
age in the תורה, Torah, you know, but yeah the גמרא Gemara.
never gave a reason.
It's best demonstration of expert testimony is My Cousin Vinny.
Right,
exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר אמימר
ומתנתו מתנה. Amar Ameimar U-matnato Matnah.
Now here's a crazy idea, not crazy but whatever, I mean it's
really like shocking.
Yes, this person can't sell land in his father's estate under the
age of twenty, but he can gift it away. Okay, now you'd
think that's even more irresponsible. Remember before the גמרא Gemara said the
guy who was irresponsible who we wouldn't allow do transactions, you know
even at the age of twenty or whatever, was the person that
was freeing the slaves. Right, that just shows general irresponsibility towards your
property. So here we're saying we don't trust him to do stuff
under the age of twenty but he can gift it, he just
can't sell it. So אמרו ליה רב אשי לאמימר השתא ומזביני דמקבל
זוזי אמרת
דלא. Amru Lei Rav Ashi Le-Ameimar Hashta U-mazvini De-mikabel Zuzei Amart De-la.
In selling where he gets money where you said that it won't
be good. Okay דילמא מוזיל ומזבין Dilma Mozil U-mazvin
maybe he'll sell it too cheaply even though you should say like
it's not so bad he got paid for it, you know, it's
not such a loss anyway. Okay, it's a rational thing to do
to sell things.
And nevertheless you say no. So כל שכן מתנה דלא מטי ליה
ולא מידי. Kol Sheken Matnah De-la Mati Leh Ve-la Midi.
So certainly a gift should not be valid, right? In the end
the estate gets nothing in exchange. It's less of a rational thing
to do. We should certainly say that's not valid. אמר ליה, he
said back to him, top of קנ"ו עמוד א'. Kuf Nun Vav
Amud Aleph. ולטעמיך, U-le-tamecha, so according to you that you think like,
you know, you want to sort of assess like did it seem
like it was a good deal or not a good deal. A
gift isn't a good deal, a sale is. So what would you
say if זבין שוי חמשא בשיתא? Zavin Shavei Chamsha Be-shita? Let's say
this guy under twenty sold land that normally is assessed at five
and he sold it at six. Like everybody said whoa he made
a nice profit there. So הכא נמי דזביניה זביני Hacha Nami De-zvinei
Zvinei would you then say it would be good? Now of course
the answer could be why not? If we're going to allow an
exception for somebody who's יודע בטיב משא ומתן, Yodea Be-tiv Massa U-mattan,
right somebody who's savvy why don't we allow an exception for a
specific transaction? But there's a difference, right? The one relates to the
גברא. Gavra. We're going to say you, given your savvy you know
all of your transactions are going to be good even though you're
under twenty because you're business savvy. And you, you're not particularly business
savvy, they're not going to be good. But are you going to
say now like we should assess case by case even somebody who
generally we don't trust? If a particular case it looks like he
made a good deal we're going to say it's good? So he
thinks that that's not logical, that הלכה Halacha cannot be distinguished, you
know, making case by case assessments like that. אלא, so we have
to say that there was a certain amount of like a לא
פלוג. Lo Pelug. קימלו להו רבנן דיינוקא מקרבא דעתיה גבי זוזי Kimu
Lehu Rabbanan De-yanuka Mekarva Da-ateh Gabbei Zuzei that a child, of course
not a child it's under twenty, but a young person they'll
be easily seduced by money. Okay, they're tempted, they're מקרבא דעתיה Mekarva
Da-ateh you know they're like eager to get their hands on cash.
Okay. ואי אמרת זביניה זביני Ve-i Amart Zvinei Zvinei if you say
that the sale will be good זימנין דמקרקשי ליה זוזי. Zimnin De-mekarkeshi
Leh Zuzei. It's that's right מקרקשי Mekarkeshi is like a great
word, jingling in the pocket.
Yeah מקרקשי Mekarkeshi is like right it's an onomatopoeia, okay, you know,
like you know like you shake the the pouch with the coins
and it go cha-cha whatever okay. ואזיל ומזבין לכולהו נכסי דאבוה. Ve-azil
U-mazvin Le-chulho Nichsei De-avuh. And then they'll sell all their father's property.
Oh my gosh a thousand dollars you imagine, I mean it's true
when you're young you know that sounds like a lot of money
you know. So
anyway so like you know you're so tempted by that number you
don't appreciate the value of like what's land going to do me?
It's a lousy piece of land, I'm not getting anything from it,
I would have to work it who knows whatever so you know
you don't have a good judgment about that and you're too easily
tempted. אבל גבי מתנה אי לאו דהוה ליה הנאה מיניה לא הוה
יהיב ליה מתנה. Aval Gabei Matnah I-lav De-hava Leh Hana'ah Mineh Lo
Hava Yahiv Leh Matnah. But מתנה Matnah there's no temptation to gift
away your land. What are you being seduced by? So since it's
not easy for people to as easy for somebody to seduce you
to give them something, right? So therefore we assume that you would
not actually gift it away unless you genuinely got some, you know,
you genuinely received something and therefore are reciprocating. Of course, the problem's
still, I don't know, it's still very funny, right? Because like, let's
say I go ahead and I, I don't know, I'm going to
take you out to a beautiful, to a ball game and then
we'll go to and then, and then I'll treat you to dinner
and I'll do all these nice things for you and I say,
you know, and then afterwards I ask you to give me a
gift of some of your property. Like, there could still be a
degree of like loss of judgment there, you know, if you can't
really assess the value of land and you're too seduced by immediate
benefit. But that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Since we don't sort
of see, you know, it's sort of like if you think about
the all of those people that like prey on, you know, well
that's the opposite, that's preying on elderly people as opposed to young
people, but you know, but they do this like part of the
whole, what's it called, scamming or con games, are all because like
you think you're getting something in the transaction, right? And because you
think you're getting something, you know, you're willing to give something up,
you know, so in that immediate transaction. So that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. Like it's in that immediate transaction where we're afraid that
they're going to be, they're going to be tricked. Okay, but a
gift is less something that you can be tricked into giving a
gift.
Sort of a funny double negative, isn't it? Like I see what
גמרא Gemara means. It's sort of what?
דמתנה? Dematana?
What do you mean?
אי לאו דהוה ליה הנאה מיניה לא הוה יהיב ליה מתנה. I
lav dehava lei hana minnei lo hava yahivei lei matana.
Were it not that you got benefit, you wouldn't be giving a
gift. So obviously you must have gotten some real benefit. But the
point is, I mean, why can't you say somebody who'll give you
like, you know, will be disproportionate to benefit you get to the
gift you give? But the point is is that if it's not
an immediate transaction, immediate exchange, we don't think that you're going to
be as likely to be tricked the same way you can, "Look,
I'm going to give you this, you give me" whatever. So that's
like more of a long-term duration type of a thing and there's,
I guess, less of a sense that the person can really be
conned as much in that case.
The idea though that he wouldn't, if he got הנאה hana from
the property, he would not gift it?
No, no, no. If he didn't get הנאה hana from the other
person, he wouldn't have gifted it away. Okay. So therefore, אמרו רבנן
תהוי מתנתו מתנה. Amru rabbanan tehei matnato matana. They allowed it to
be good. Now, and now, maybe partly because of this problem, like,
I don't know, so big deal, but why not just give him
that protection? Right? Okay, maybe it's not exactly the same risk, but
why not protect it? I mean, what's the benefit of letting him
gift something? Look at it that way, right? Like, okay, maybe he's
not as much at risk, but as once we've prevented him from
selling, let's prevent him from giving a gift to protect him. What
does he have to lose if you don't allow the gift to
be good? So then the גמרא Gemara adds in this extra line,
so אמרו רבנן תהוי מתנתו מתנה דליעבדו ליה מילי. Amru rabbanan tehei
matnato matana dilaavdu lei mili. That people
should not hesitate to do favors for him. Like if they feel
that this kid can't give any gifts, okay, it's an interesting type
of society, nobody will do any favors for him. Of course, he
can give gifts with מטלטלין, just don't give gifts with קרקע. karka.
I mean, a gift with קרקע karka is pretty exceptional that somebody
would gift away land. So it really remains like, I don't know,
you know, it really remains curious why they allowed it. Like even
after you're done saying that the risk isn't as high, once they've,
you know, restricted him with his father's estate, with the, you know,
and that's really for his own good or for his brothers' good,
his family's good, they should do it in a case of a
gift as well. I really don't understand it.
Okay, utilitarian for the child, for the young person.
Right, but the question is like, does it make sense? I mean,
if you look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam דליעבדו ליה מילי, dilaavdu lei
mili, like six lines down in the narrow lines, לגמול לו חסד
ולהטיב לו בכל ענינים. ligmol lo chesed ulehaitiv lo bechol inyanim. Well,
I guess people feel like, "Let's constantly do good, maybe he'll gift
me a piece of land." So the very, so holding out the
possibility will get people to, "Oh my God, you know, this kid,
he just inherited his father's building on Central Park West or whatever,
let's start really showering him with kindness." So if you know that
there's that little possibility he'll give you a gift of land. So
the idea would be that he would be advised to never gift
the land, but the fact that he has the possibility of doing
it gets everybody to be nice to him. Okay, anyway. אמר רב
נחמן אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel. Both, okay, now we're
going to sort of wrap this up since we're talking about the
necessary age for selling land, we're going to talk about the necessary
ages in general. Now of course, the normal ages that are of
relevance are בר ובת מצוה. Bar uBat Mitzvah. So we're not going
to open that discussion, but what we are going to talk about
is whether you have to, because remember, part of the whole issue
of let's disinter our brother there and check if he had the
pubic hairs. So the question here is like when do you have
to directly identify that the person has the pubic hairs, you know,
and when can you just assume that they're an adult because of
their age? Now one thing by the way I should say, not
discussed in this גמרא Gemara but in another גמרא, gemara is that
for men, for boys, facial hair is an evidence of pubic hair.
So at least it says, no, is, so of course that avoids
having to do a direct, you know, check in terms of the
pubic hairs. But anyway, let's take a look at what the גמרא
gemara says when you need direct evidence. The general principle that I'll
just say one more thing before we read this, there's something called
חזקה דרבא, Chazakah de'Rava, רבא's Rava חזקה. Chazakah. רבא Rava basically said
it's a חזקה Chazakah once a boy reaches thirteen and a girl
reaches twelve that they have the pubic hairs, and the גמרא gemara
says that you can rely on that for—I mean the conclusion להלכה
le'halachah is that you can rely on that for דרבנן de'Rabbanan and
not for דאורייתא. de'Oraita. So that's basically why we let a kid
at like bar mitzvah, you know, read from the תורה Torah because
that's only a rabbinic institution. But when you get to something like,
you know, פרשת זכור Parshat Zachor which is assumed to be like
דאורייתא, de'Oraita, the reading from the תורה, Torah, or let, I don't
know, to do תקיעת שופר tekiat shofar or something like that, you
know, you would not allow it just because the kid is bar
mitzvah. So you would either need, you know, like somebody like, you
know, the father to testify, and then the question is whose testimony
is the father's testimony good? You need עדות, like what is the
implications for it, okay, yeah, no, that's a little circular asking the
קטן, because if you don't yet know he's an adult, you can't
trust his own testimony, he's not yet an adult to testify. Anyway,
but, facial hair, facial hair of course would be a good way
of dealing with it in the case of boys. So let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara So אמר
רב נחמן אמר שמואל בודקין לקידושין לגירושין לחליצה ולמיאונין. Amar Rav Nachman
amar Shmuel bodkin le'kiddushin le'geirushin le'chalitzah u'le'miunin. Okay, for marriage, so a
boy thirteen gave כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin to a girl who was,
you know, whatever, who was bat mitzvah already. Okay, so let's say
the girl was definitely an adult, but is it a good marriage?
And the relevance is, well, a lot of relevance, but an easy
one is like you, you know, you can't say oh let's just
be מחמיר machmir and assume it's good, because let's say now this
young woman accepts קידושין kiddushin from a different man. So if you
say that the first one was ודאי vadai good, the second קידושין
kiddushin is ודאי vadai not good. But if the first one is
a ספק, safeik, then she's going to need a גט get from
the second man. Everybody understand that, right? Yes. So therefore, if you
want to ascertain whether the first one, certainly if you didn't know
you'd be מחמיר, machmir, but being מחמיר machmir doesn't solve the problem,
there are cases where there's consequences in both directions. So if you
want to know for sure it's not enough to know the boy
was bar mitzved, you have to know he had pubic hairs, or
the reverse. If the girl is bat mitzvah. Now it's true that
a girl can be married under bat mitzvah but through her father.
But let's say she accepted כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin directly, not through
her father. Can you assume that she was bat mitzvah or not?
Right, it's not enough that she was twelve, you have to know
that there was pubic hairs to know that it was ודאי vadai
a good קידושין. kiddushin. So that's קידושין. kiddushin.
גירושין Geirushin is they're married and he now is writing a גט.
get. So the only way a man can write a גט get
is if he's an adult, so you have to check. Okay, לחליצה
le'chalitzah
that both, for חליצה chalitzah to be good, you need both the
both parties to be adults. So in order to know that it
was a good חליצה, chalitzah, you would have to do a direct,
you know, check. ולמיאונין. u'le'miunin.
How did they do גירושין geirushin without the קידושין? kiddushin? So that's
what the גמרא's Gemara going to ask. Okay, once you checked for
the קידושין, kiddushin, you know the answer for the גירושין. geirushin. So
the גמרא's Gemara. going to say that.
There is no concept here of קידושין דרבנן, kiddushin de'Rabbanan, we had
that in כתובות. Ketubot. What was it called?
Yeah, מיאון, miun,
we're that's about the next line. ולמיאונין. u'le'miunin.
So יבום Yibum
was
thrown in here too, right?
What?
יבום Yibum was normally thrown in here too.
For, well, no, יבום yibum can possibly work by קטן.
And that's why גירושין's geirushin out, well,
that's what the גמרא's Gemara. going to say.
Okay, so למיאונין, le'miunin, everybody's one step ahead. מיאון Miun is a
girl's married off by her brothers or mother if her father isn't
alive, and that when she's under age, that's rabbinic, and then she
can למאן, lema'ein, she can reject her husband until she becomes bat
mitzvah, just verbally reject and it voids the marriage. Once she becomes
bat mitzvah and she stays within the marriage, then it requires a
גט. get. So here you want to check that she's still a
minor to understand that the מיאון miun is good.
Okay. ולמכר בנכסי אביו, u'le'machar be'nichsei aviv, but when it comes to
selling the father's property, there it's not enough to check for the
pubic hairs, עד שיהיה בן עשרים. ad she'yehei ben esrim. That's what
we've been saying. Okay, וכיון דבדקנו, ve'keivan de'badkanu, now the גמרא's Gemara
going to analyze that. וכיון דבדקנו לקידושין, ve'keivan de'badkanu le'kiddushin, if we
checked for קידושין kiddushin to say that it was good, לגירושין למה
לי, le'geirushin lamah li, why do I need to check again for
גירושין? geirushin? So the גמרא Gemara says לא נצרכא אלא ליבום, lo
nitzrecha ela le'yibum, it's for יבום, yibum, דתנן בן תשע שנים ויום
אחד שבא על יבימתו קנאה. de'tenan ben taysha shanim ve'yom echad she'ba
al yevimto kna'ah. Okay, that the הלכה halachah by יבום yibum is
the act of intercourse, it's not an act
and therefore it's just the, you know, almost the reality, it's not
a formal act of קניין kinyan like קידושין kiddushin is, right? The
גמרא Gemara says that even if the act of intercourse didn't realize
that it was his sister-in-law, גמרא Gemara even discusses a case of
accidental intercourse, it's almost just like the physical reality of intercourse creates
the marriage by יבום, yibum, but the participants have to be the
right age for it to be considered significant. So the boy would
have to be nine years old and a day. So therefore it
can be that the woman is legally married through this act of
יבום yibum and it's דאורייתא de'Oraita married, and you didn't and you're
not yet certain whether the boy is an adult or not and
whether he can. of a גט. get. So that would be a
case you would have to check is if he was thirteen and
two hairs in order to give a
גט. get. Okay, ואינו עושה גט עד שיגדיל. ve'eino ose get ad
sheyagdil.
That's the end of that משנה. Mishnah. So yes, the ייבום yibbum
works, but for a גט get he has to be an adult.
And that's why you'd have to check. Now, לחליצה, lechalitza, when it
says you have to check for חליצה, chalitza, לאפוקי מדרבי יוסי. le'apukei
mid'rabbi yose. That's to reject the position of רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yose.
Meaning implicitly it means you have to check both the boy and
the girl. And that rejects the position of רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose,
דאמר, de'amar, איש כתוב בפרשה. ish katuv baparasha. It says when it
speaks about the אשה isha about ייבום yibbum and חליצה, chalitza, it
says what does it say? It says
what's the
פסוק? pasuk? כי ישבו אחים יחדיו ומת
אחד מהם ובן אין לו לא תהיה אשת המת החוצה לאיש זר
יבמה
יבא עליה...
ואם לא יחפוץ האיש.
ki yeshvu achim yachdav umet echad mehem uven ein lo lo tihiye
eshet hamet hachutza le'ish zar yevamah yavo
aleha... ve'im lo yachpotz ha'ish.
יחפוץ האיש. yachpotz ha'ish. Right, יחפוץ האיש. yachpotz ha'ish. So it says
until then it says brother-in-law, sister-in-law, but when it uses the word
to say man, it says האיש, ha'ish, but it never says אשה.
isha. So he says,
איש כתוב בפרשה אבל אשה בין גדולה בין קטנה. ish katuv baparasha
aval isha bein gdola bein ktana. She could be part of the
חליצה chalitza act the same way the ייבום yibbum act didn't require
adults, the חליצה chalitza act, he's the only actor, it's the way
it's imagining it, maybe like a גט. get. He's the primary actor,
so right, a גט get can be given to a minor girl,
because she's just passive and receives the גט. get. So רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose imagines the same is true by חליצה. chalitza. Right? Even
though the גמרא Gemara speaks about the woman's activity in חליצה, chalitza,
she's a more active party in חליצה chalitza than she is by
a גט, get, he says fundamentally she does not have to be
an adult, only he has to be an adult. איש כתוב בפרשה
אבל אשה בין קטנה בין גדולה. ish katuv baparasha aval isha bein
ktana bein gdola. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so since this
is saying you check and presumably without specifying it means you check
both parties, so קא משמע לן דמקישינן אשה לאיש, ka mashma lan
demakshinan isha le'ish, שלא כרבי יוסי. shelo kerabbi yose. No, the woman
is just like the man, so both parties have to be adults,
so for חליצה chalitza we would have to check not just that
he was an adult but that she was an adult as well.
Okay, ולמיאונים, ulmi'unim, now מיאון, mi'un, לאפוקי מדרבי יהודה. le'apukei mid'rabbi yehuda.
Since it's sort of categorizing it with the other forms of checking,
presumably it just means the standard checking of two pubic hairs. So
that would go against רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, דאמר עד שירבה שחור.
de'amar ad sheyirbe shachor. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says that for מיאון
mi'un the girl can reject her husband until not just when she's
technically an adult of two pubic hairs, but it has to be
a lot of pubic hairs, ירבה שחור. yirbe shachor. Okay, which another
גמרא Gemara? says it means that they're sort of laying flat against
her skin. Okay, so קא משמע לן דלא כרבי יהודה. ka mashma
lan delo kerabbi yehuda. So since it compares this checking with the
other checking, presumably it means the standard definition of adulthood which is
two pubic hairs which is not רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda different definition
for purposes of מיאונים. mi'unim. ולמכור בנכסי אביו עד שיהיה בן עשרים,
ulimkor benichsei aviv ad sheyehe ben esrim, and for selling the father's
estate you have to be twenty, לאפוקי ממאן דאמר בן שמונה עשרה,
le'apukei miman de'amar ben shmoneh esreh, to reject the position we had
earlier of רבא Rava of eighteen. Here it's a position of twenty.
So that's a nice little summary of different areas of הלכה halakha
of adulthood and checking adulthood. And now, just to make Michael even
happier, we have a whole string of הלכתות. hilchosos. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara, says, והלכתא, vehilchata, הלכה halacha is, תוך זמן כלפני זמן,
toch zman
kilfnei zman, during the twentieth year you're still under age, you have
to actually be twenty and a day. Okay, והלכתא כגידל בר מנשיא,
vehilchata kegiddel bar menashya, we rule like גידל בר מנשיא Giddel bar
Menashya who said that if the person is particularly savvy in areas
of business even if they're under age it works. והלכתא כמר זוטרא,
vehilchata kemar zutra, we rule like מר זוטרא Mar Zutra who says
what did מר זוטרא say?
Oh, yeah, that for עדות, they could be good for עדות מטלטלין
edut metaltelin but they're not good for עדות קרקע. edut karka. Okay,
that distinction between מטלטלין and קרקע. karka. They cannot testify on קרקע
karka when they're under savvy, right? But when it's still in the
case when they're under the age of twenty. והלכתא כאמימר, vehilchata ke'ameimar,
we rule like אמימר Ameimar that actually a gift is good even
though for us, for me that certainly seems strange. He said the
only thing that's not good is a sale, but a gift is
good, we rule that way. והלכתא כרב נחמן אמר שמואל בכולהו, vehilchata
kerav nachman amar shmuel bekulhu, and we rule like this last section
of רב נחמן אמר שמואל Rav Nachman amar Shmuel of all the
different people that you check, have to check to make sure they're
בר/בת מצוה bar/bat mitzvah for, you know, for marriage, for divorce, for
all these various things.
Okay, question is these days like, you know, we have very practical
things. If the kid inherits an estate between the age of
twenty and he wants to transact. I mean is there still checking
like in the business world?
I mean in general that's a question in how much of any
of the דיני ממונות dinei mamonot we do nowadays is governed much
more by דינא דמלכותא, dina demalchuta, right? Than it is by חושן
משפט. choshen mishpat. You know, but in theory, I mean if we
were running by חושן משפט choshen mishpat the answer would be yes.
So no relative can say, "Hey wait a minute, this kid...", yeah.
Let's do the opposite. Let's say somebody is like I don't know
what, what's the, do you have to be like in secular law,
you have to be like an age like eighteen for a transaction
to be valid? Or like...
If it's as
long as it's your own money,
could you be five years old and it's your own money? Is
there a difference between buying the car and buying the candy bar?
I don't, okay. So can somebody be five years old and if
they inherited money
is it a valid transaction? Sometimes yeah, that's right, yes, it's license-specific
to cars like. Oh,
but
I just mean like if it's a large thing, right? A thousand
dollars worth, like a thousand dollar Babe Ruth baseball card, right?
So that's good, like if you're 10 years old, you have a
thousand dollars or whatever, is that like- how about the problem the
גמרא's Gemara dealing with? You can easily be tricked, right? I don't
know what regulates ages of being engaging in transactions in in general
law, but anyway, but the point could be you could imagine a
case where in הלכה Halacha it would be valid, a six or
seven year old, and secular law would say it wouldn't be valid,
like we're constantly- and the other way around, we're constantly living in
a world in which our entire reality in דיני ממונות Dinei Mamonos
is governed by דינא דמלכותא Dina D'Malchusa and we tend to default
to the דינא דמלכותא. Dina D'Malchusa. Yeah, I mean, well that's, like,
look, that's the general question of דינא דמלכותא, Dina D'Malchusa, but in
דיני ממונות Dinei Mamonos it very much dominates דינא דמלכותא. Dina D'Malchusa.
All right, so, so now the- so now let's go on to
the next משנה. Mishnah, המחלק נכסיו על פיו, Hamechalek nechasav al piv,
so finally, finally we are going to get to a משנה, Mishnah
we remember we dealt with an earlier משנה Mishnah. that dealt with
a מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shechiv Meira and whether it was חוזר,
Chozer, but that- right, whether when the guy got better it reversed.
But that never dealt with the question about what I've been saying
all along is like what you know in ישיבה Yeshiva you're term-
you're taught as the first major principle of מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas
Shechiv Meira ככתובים ומסורים דמו. Kechisuvim Umesurim Damu. It doesn't require a
קנין, Kinyan, it's done just verbally. The גמרא Gemara, introduced it and
had all of these debates. Does that apply? Is that true? Does
it apply by במקצת Bimiktzas or only by בכולו, Bekulo, מצוה מחמת
מיתה, Mitzvah machmas misa, etcetera. So here actually we had all that
discussion earlier, but here we're going to find that it actually is
getting introduced by this משנה. Mishnah Okay, so let's take a look.
This question about this, whether it's effective by the verbal words.
There's something called the Minors Contracts Act that specifies that a minor
can enter into a contract if it is deemed to be fair
and reasonable by the court.
Oh, I interesting,
the default is yes, but
if it's shown that basically- I see. And would the same be
true if it was a sale? Like a contract means oh yes,
any like transaction. Aha, interesting.
Same question as the סוגיא, Sugya,
except, except there the point is the default is yes, but then
it could be voided by the court essentially, right.
Question in the סוגיא Sugya is what's the default?
Right, exactly, okay.
That one sounds like they look at the individual transaction,
right, one by one, right, not have some rules based on age
or whatever. Exactly, exactly. Okay. המחלק נכסיו על פיו, Hamechalek nechasav al
piv, somebody there is in their deathbed and distributing their property, presumably
it's a מתנת שכיב מרע בכולו. Matnas Shechiv Meira Bekulo.
רבי אלעזר אומר Rabbi Elazar Omer אחד בריא ואחד מסוכן, Echad bari
ve'echad mesukan, whether he is healthy or whether he is in danger,
so it's whether it's the deathbed case or a normal case or
a sickbed case, נכסים שיש להם אחריות נקנים בכסף בשטר ובחזקה ושאין
להם אחריות אין נקנים אלא במשיכה. Nechasim sheyeish lahem achrayus niknin bekesef
beshtar uvachazakah veshein lahem achrayus ein niknin ela bimshicha. I don't believe
in any special power of מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shechiv Meira in
terms of that you know, in terms of what effects the transaction.
Okay, if it's land then it's כסף שטר וחזקה, Kesef shtar vachazakah,
money, a writ or taking, you know, doing an act of showing
of, like, improving the land, and if it's chattel then it's משיכה,
Meshicha, it's drawing it near, you need a normal קנין. Kinyan. The
previous משנה Mishnah. said that a מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shechiv Meira
if he gets better is voided, that's one thing, that was only
given on the anticipation of death, so if he gets better it's
voided, but in terms of what you need to effect the transaction,
רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar is like the agnostic or the heretic, he
says there's no special rule of a מתנת שכיב מרע, Matnas Shechiv
Meira, you need a normal קנין. Kinyan. Okay.
Even if the guy got better or not, the other party didn't
do משיכה, Meshicha, still be חוזר. Chozer.
Exactly. If the guy died, מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shechiv Meira distributed
it all, he died or whatever, if there was no קנין Kinyan
it didn't take effect, you need a normal קנין. Kinyan.
What, what do you mean he's an agnostic or a heretic, he
just disagrees with the-
I know what I mean by that is is that it is
so, like, it is so- what's the word- like, right, meaning I'm
talking from my experience as a- as a ישיבה בחור, Yeshiva bochur,
okay, where like it's like, this is what מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas
Shechiv Meira is! Foundation! מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shechiv Meira means that
even verbally you effect the קנין. Kinyan. Like אמר חוזר Amar Chozer
is like a who like whatever you know marginal point. The major
חידוש Chiddush of מתנת שכיב מרע Matnas Shechiv Meira is חז"ל allowed
him to verbally create a קנין Kinyan and he just completely rejects
that idea. Okay. אמרו לו, Amru lo, so anyway, but by the
way, here is an interesting question for him: if he does a
קנין, Kinyan, when does it take effect? Maybe he's not a complete
heretic about this new category of מתנת שכיב מרע. Matnas Shichiv Meyra.
Maybe he would say you do a קניין, Kinyan, it still takes
effect after you die, okay, right? Because as opposed to a normal
מתנת ברי Matnas Bari takes effect now? Or not? It sounds more,
without him saying otherwise, that he rejects the entire idea. The entire
idea that there's this special institution. So for him, it would really
be hard, right? Because or it wouldn't affect property that the person
acquires after they do it and so on. Okay, so for him
it seems to just have the מתנת ברי Matnas Bari track.
אמרו לו, Amru Lo, they said to him, מעשה באמם של בני
רוחל, Maaseh Be'imam Shel Bnei Rochel, there's a story about the mother
of these kids of רוחל, Rochel, which was the name of the
father, שהייתה חולה, She'hayetah Cholah, she was sick, ואמרה תנו כבינתי לבתי,
Ve'amrah Tenu Kevinnati Levitti,
give my necklace to my daughter, והיא בשנים עשר מנה, Ve'hi Beshneim
Asar Maneh, it was very expensive, twelve מנה, Maneh, ומתה, U'metah, and
she died, וקיימו את דבריה, Ve'kiyyemu Es Devaryah, and they did it,
even though that was completely verbal, there was no קניין Kinyan or
whatever. אמר להם, Amar Lahem, he said to them, בני רוחל תקברם
אמם, Bnei Rochel Tikberem Imam, let them the sons of רוחל Rochel
as opposed to the daughter, their mother should bury them, okay? Here
the mother predeceases the kids, but the basic point is like the
sons didn't deserve the mother's property, so the חכמים Chachamim were happy
to give it to the daughter. And therefore it was an exception,
it wasn't really a legally binding type of a thing. So who
was their sons and why were they not deserving of their mother's
property? So we'll see in the גמרא. But his basic answer was
that either that case was totally bogus, it didn't happen, it shouldn't
have happened, that's sort of what a surface reading would sound like,
or saying like, yeah fine it happened, but that was a special
exception that the חכמים Chachamim made. Okay, so let's take a look
at the גמרא. תניא, Tanya, אמר להן רבי אליעזר לחכמים, Amar Lahen
Rabbi Eliezer Lechachamim, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, now there's a whole question
is it רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar or אליעזר, Eliezer, that's going to
be relevant for the next משנה. Mishnah, So we'll discuss that in
a minute. Okay, but said to them רבי אליעזר לחכמים, Rabbi Eliezer
Lechachamim, מעשה במרוני אחד, Maaseh Bemeroni Echad, there was a story about
a certain man from מירון, Meron, שהיה בירושלים, Shehayah Biyerushalayim, he was
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, והיו לו מטלטלין הרבה, Vehayu Lo Metaltelin Harbeh, and
he had all of this property, וביקש ליתנם במתנה, Uvikkesh Litnam Bematana,
and
he wanted to gift it away, ואמרו לו, Ve'amru Lo, and they
said to him, אין להם תקנה עד שיקנם אגב קרקע, Ein Lahem
Takkanah Ad Sheyiknem Agav Karka, if you really want to gift it
all away, then you'll have to do a normal קניין. Kinyan. And
the best way to do a קניין Kinyan now by מטלטלין you
could do
משיכה, Meshicha, but that's a lot of מטלטלין to שלעפ shlep if
you imagine he has tons and tons of hundreds of thousands of
sheep and camels and gold or whatever, who's going to do משיכה?
Meshicha? Now another way of course would be a קניין סודר, Kinyan
Sudar, that would be the easy way, but for whatever reason he's
not doing סודר, Sudar, he's doing a קניין אגב. Kinyan Agav. You
give somebody a little bit of land and you can give them
as much מטלטלין as you want. So what did he do? הלך
ולקח בית סלע אחד סמוך לירושלים, Halach Velakach Beis Sela Echad Samuch
Liyerushalayim, he took a certain plot of land, ואמר, Ve'amar, and he
said, צפונו לפלוני, Tzephono Leploni,
the northern piece part of this land should go to ראובן, Reuven,
ועמו מאה צאן ומאה חביות, Ve'immo Me'ah Tzon Ume'ah Chaviyot,
and with it he should get a hundred sheep and a hundred
barrels of wine. ודרומו לפלוני ועמו מאה צאן ומאה חביות. Udaromo Leploni
Ve'immo Me'ah Tzon Ume'ah Chaviyot. And he did all this stuff and
he used that to distribute all his property, ומת וקיימו חכמים את
דבריו, Umes Vekiyemu Chachamim Es Devarav, and he died, and therefore they
established. But it says oh look, he needed to do a real
קניין, Kinyan, he couldn't just verbally distribute his property. So that proves
what I said. אמרו לו, Amru Lo, they said back to him,
משם ראיה, Misham Rayah, that you from you want to bring a
proof from there? מרוני ברי היה, Meroni Bari Hayah, he was a
healthy guy. He died, he didn't die because he was sick when
he was distributing it. He was healthy when he distributed it and
then he just died afterwards, he had some accident, okay? So they're
basically arguing whether he was a שכיב מרע. Shichiv Meyra. Sure he'd
need a normal קניין, Kinyan, he wasn't a שכיב מרע. Shichiv Meyra
And רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi Eliezer's version of the story was he was
a שכיב מרע Shichiv Meyra and he still needed a normal קניין.
Kinyan. Okay, so for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer a שכיב מרע Shichiv
Meyra. needs a normal קניין. Kinyan. Well אלעזר Elazar
or אליעזר? Eliezer?
We'll
discuss that in a minute. Okay, let's bracket the אליעזר אלעזר Eliezer
Elazar thing for a minute. Anyway, but the point is for him,
for whoever the תנא קמא Tana Kama is of our משנה, Mishnah
it needs a normal קניין Kinyan and he understood that that case
was a שכיב מרע. Shichiv Meyra. And the חכמים Chachamim say back
the reason it needed
the קניין Kinyan was he wasn't a שכיב מרע. Shichiv Meyra.
But it still works with him too because he said ברי Bari
needs a normal קניין Kinyan also. Suppose I have a thing that's
דברי הכל, Divrei Hakol, right? That a ברי Bari needs...
Yeah, it's not a proof against him, but he thought it was
a proof for him and the answer was it doesn't prove your
case because the guy wasn't a שכיב מרע. shchiv mera Okay, אמרו
להן, Amru Lahen, so now in that was a case that he
was bringing to support his case, but in the משנה Mishnah, the
חכמים Chachamim brought a case to support their position. The case of
בני רוחל Bnei Rochel where a קניין Kinyan wasn't needed and with
this case of the necklace. And his response back to that was
let their mother bury the sons. מאי טעמא קלטינהו, Mai Taama Kalatinhu,
why is he cursing out the sons? Again, the point is by...
The sons didn't deserve the mother's property, so therefore it was fine
that they gave the necklace to the daughter, even though she really
didn't, she legally didn't own it. So why is he cursing out
their sons? אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel
מקיימי קוצים בכרם היו mekayamei kotzim bekarem hayu because they, the sons,
basically kept thorn bushes present in the vineyard. So is that כלאים?
kilayim? You're not allowed to grow mixed seeds, and you're not even
allowed to allow mixed growths to occur within your vineyard. You would
have to uproot it. But is a thorn bush really like a
type of a vegetable? Is it a plant? Is it something that's
eaten? If it's a weed, if it's not eaten, is it a
problem? So we're going to see that there's a debate whether that's
a כלאים kilayim problem because some places would feed these thorn bushes
to like
their... right. Who was it in Winnie the Pooh, the one, Eeyore,
that always eats the thorns and the thistles? What is he, is
he a donkey? Yeah. I mean, you wonder like what animal can
actually eat thorns and thistles? Can donkeys really do that? How do
they do it? What do they have? They have like metal in
their mouths or something? I don't know. Anyway, fine. So that was
the issue. Okay. So, and the reason he, and now it's not,
he, and apparently what the גמרא says is, they're not just debating
like whether this case was an exception or not, but where he
actually looked at these kids of the בני ממן Bnei Mamon and
he said they're doing something wrong, etc., and that became the lens
through which he interpreted this case. And the חכמים Chachamim actually thought
they didn't do anything wrong by leaving the thorn bushes around. So
let's take a look. Okay. רבי אליעזר לטעמיה, Rabbi Eliezer letamei, he's
going according to his reasoning. דתנן במתניתין, De'tanan bematnitin, המקיים קוצים בכרם,
hamekayem kotzim bekarem, if you leave the thorns growing in the vineyard.
רבי אליעזר אומר קדש, Rabbi Eliezer omer kadesh, or
קידש, kidesh, they become sanctified, meaning they become כלאים, kilayim, they become
אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, and it's a transgression. וחכמים אומרים לא קידש,
Ve'chachamim omrim lo kidesh, they do not. אלא דבר שכמוהו מקיימים, Ella
davar shekamoho mekayemim, only stuff that normal people sort of plant and
want to grow, you know, and want to use as a type
of a crop, right, and want to sort of intentionally grow it.
But something like this, which is essentially a weed, that's not a
כלאים kilayim problem.
Would a rose bush be the same thing? Because it has thorns,
I mean, a rose bush would be the same thing because it
has thorns.
Oh, that's an interesting question. Would it have to be food? Let's
say you'd be מקיים mekayem it but for non-food purposes. That's a
good question. I have to check that.
Okay.
בשלמא כרכום חזי, Bi'shlama karkom hachazei, if it was something like saffron,
so okay, you know, that I would get, that's not a weed,
that's actually a spice. אלא קוצים למאי חזי, Ella kotzim lemai hazei,
but
thorns, what good is that? אמר רב חנינא מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר,
Amar Rav Chanina mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Eliezer, so what's רבי אליעזר's Rabbi
Eliezer reasoning?
שכן בערביא מקיימים קוצים בשדות לגמליהם. Sheken ba'arvaya mekayemim kotzim besadot legamleihem.
They actually specifically sustain and they want these thorns to be growing
in order to feed to their camels. So because of that, רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer looks at these kids and he's saying they're doing
a terrible thing, they're keeping כלאים, kilayim, I'm going to interpret the
case that the reason they gave the necklace to the daughter was
that they didn't want the sons to have it because the sons
were רשעים, resha'im, they were doing this. And the חכמים Chachamim look
at the case and say the sons weren't doing anything wrong. So
if they're giving the necklace to the daughter, it must have been
because it was a legally binding transaction. Yes, Eli.
First of all, sounds like such a metaphor.
Right, קוצים בכרם, kotzim bekarem, right.
And second of all, but the
גמרא does use it as a metaphor elsewhere, that קוצים בכרם, kotzim
bekarem, like you know, but anyway, yeah.
And it's kind of like, like really, just because they agreed with
the חכמים Chachamim or they conducted themselves like the חכמים, Chachamim, you're
going to confiscate their property? It sounds like there was something political
going on here with the חכמים. Chachamim.
What was this really about?
Oh, you mean reading the whole thing as like a symbolic, like
some deeper type of debate going on here. Yeah, that's a good
point. You need a better like דרשן darshan in order to pierce
that. But you're right, you could certainly read this as a deeper
thing. Okay, so the גמרא says like
this: אמר רב לוי, Amar Rav Levi, קונין קנין משכיב מרע, konin
kinyan mishchiv mera, fine. So that's the debate. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says there's no such thing as a שכיב מרע shchiv mera. verbal
קנין. kinyan. As I said, the question is, does he reject the
whole institution of מתנת שכיב מרע? matnat shchiv mera? Would it take
effect in life or after death or whatever? But the חכמים Chachamim
say, as we're familiar with it, even a verbal thing. Now we're
going to have another statement, which is somewhat related. אמר רב לוי,
Amar Rav Levi, קונין קנין משכיב מרע אפילו בשבת. konin kinyan mishchiv
mera afilu be'Shabbat. If it's on שבת, Shabbat, you can do a
קנין kinyan from a שכיב מרע. shchiv mera Now the funny thing
is that you don't need, well yeah, you don't need to do
a קנין kinyan for a שכיב מרע shchiv mera according to the
חכמים. Chachamim. Although there are cases where the חכמים Chachamim you would
need. What would be the cases where for the חכמים Chachamim you
would need to do a קנין kinyan for it to be binding?
Does anybody remember?
I'm sorry, what?
When for the חכמים Chachamim would you need to do a קנין
kinyan for a שכיב מרע shchiv mera for it to be binding?
Well, in terms of being חוזר, chozer, something like that, right?
Well, to prevent him from being חוזר chozer for מקצת נכסים. miktzat
nechasim. Okay, so there could be a case where if he wants
to give it on שבת, Shabbat, there could be two scenarios. One
is he's giving כל נכסיו, kol nechasav, so for the חכמים Chachamim
you don't even need it. So you could say you shouldn't do
a קנין, kinyan, it looks like a violation of שבת Shabbat to
do a קנין kinyan and there's not even a need for doing
it. Get, okay, so that you could say or it could be
מקצת נכסיו. mikzas nechasav. Now there you could say, there maybe I
could accept the idea, okay, do a קנין, kinyan, it is necessary.
Or you could say the opposite. You could say if it's כל
נכסיו, kol nechasav, the קנין kinyan is just for show and it's
not as much of a violation. If it's מקצת נכסיו mikzas nechasav
and you need the קנין kinyan and it's a real קנין, kinyan,
that you shouldn't do. But the basic position here is either way,
this is the way the רשב"ם interprets it, whether it's כל נכסיו
kol nechasav and somewhat not necessary, whether it's מקצת נכסיו mikzas nechasav
and a real קנין, kinyan, either way you could do it even
on שבת. Shabbos. Why? So קונין קנין משכיב מרע אפילו בשבת konyin
kinyan mishchiv mera afilu beShabbat ולא לחוש לדברי רבי אליעזר, v'lo lachosh
lidvrei Rabbi Eliezer, it's not because Rabbi Eliezer says that it's not
binding without a קנין, kinyan, even if it would be binding without
a קנין, kinyan, אלא שמא תטרוף דעתו עליו. ela shema titrof daato
alav. You don't want him to get so anxious and agitated that,
"Oh my God, I'm going to die before שבת Shabbos is over
and this won't be binding," and so on. And even if it
would be binding, you say, "No, no, no, שכיב מרע shchiv mera.
works, it's just verbal, it works." You say, "No, no, no, I
want to make sure, I want to make sure it's good, I
want to whatever." So just to calm him down you do it.
So you do it whether it's unnecessary, it's a כלו, kolo, or
and it sounds like from the גמרא you certainly do it if
it is necessary. According to Rabbi Eliezer, if it was a case
of מקצת, mikzas, you would certainly do a קנין kinyan because it's
necessary. So here are concessions we're making even on הלכות שבת, hilchot
Shabbat, right? Not just that we're going to make an innovation to
allow a new type of a קנין kinyan so לא תטרוף דעתו,
lo titrof daato, which is the whole institution of שכיב מרע. shchiv
mera. Here we're willing to at least override rabbinic concerns of שבת
Shabbat שמא תטרוף דעתו. shema titrof daato. And I think I said
earlier that רב Rav Moshe Feinstein
uses this idea of טירוף דעת tirof daas when somebody's will is
being frustrated in a number of very important issues in medical ethics.
I said this before, but it's worth saying again. You know, הלכה
halakha does not have much of a place for autonomy in medical
decisions, because if there's a מצוה to preserve a life, then why
should you as a patient have the place to say like, "I
don't want to take medication, I don't want to do this," etc.?
It should be that the decision should be made based on what
is necessary, most necessary to preserve a life. Now there are cases
where autonomy makes sense because there's a question of risk. Am I
required to do an operation that has a high degree of risk
and even if it's and you know for somebody let's say they're
terminal and even if it's successful it only extends the life a
little bit? Like, there's not a clear answer to what the right
thing to do to preserve a life there is. So there there's
a place for autonomy. But if a patient basically is refusing medication
that all the doctors agree are necessary
for the person's health, why should they be able to say no?
So but of course in contemporary medicine, right, there's autonomy rules. So
רב Rav Moshe creates this backdoor to give the place for autonomy,
not in an absolute sense but in a large sense based on
the principle of טירוף דעת tirof daas that starts with שכיב מרע.
shchiv mera And you see by the שכיב מרע shechiv mera. if
his desires or whatever are going to be frustrated, we're afraid it's
going to hasten his death. So רב Rav Moshe says, "Yes, it's
all about preserving the life and it's not fundamentally about autonomy." But
if a person is saying, "I don't want to take this medication,
I don't want to take it, I don't want to take it,"
and they're actively resisting, then he says forcing them to take the
medication is a greater סכנת נפשות. sakanat nefashos. You know, now of
course it's not always true, case by case you should decide whether
it is or it isn't, but רב Rav Moshe says as a
general rule we are going to assume that the טירוף דעת tirof
daas is going to be a bigger problem than the not giving
of the medication. Now here the גמרא uses it to compromise a
דרבנן derabbanan on שבת. Shabbos. You know, would that be enough to
risk?
Because you're actually, some of these are דאורייתא, de'oraisa, if if...
Well, the דאורייתא de'oraisa is saving a life.
Like, how would I be over this דאורייתא, de'oraisa, meaning...
No, in the גמרא? Yeah.
You said דרבנן derabbanan is the קנין. kinyan.
You're not allowed to do transactions on שבת Shabbos and we're overriding
it because of the concern of טירוף דעת. tirof daas.
The whole transaction is דרבנן? derabbanan?
Yes, the whole איסור issur of transactions is דרבנן. derabbanan. So so
that's one thing, that the טירוף דעת tirof daas concerns override דרבננ'ס.
derabbanans. But again, רב Moshe takes it and expands it and lets
it play a significant role in medical
ethics issues.
It's interesting. So what's the difference between the halakhic application of this
concept of טירוף דעת tirof daas and like in במה מדליקין bameh
madlikin and מכבה מפני רוח רעה mechabeh mipnei ruach ra or somebody
that's got a psychodynamic angst and pain?
Right, so there are other sources, right, there are other sources of
ישוב הדעת, yishuv hadaas, like the pregnant woman who says she has
to eat on יום כיפור Yom Kippur and you give it to
her for ישוב הדעת. yishuv hadaas. Right, so I'd have to check
like why רב Moshe, like it's not the only example of it,
but I think it's the it's the best example of somebody like
somebody's anxiety and frustration about their will not being not being taken
care of, right?
So in the other case if it's like רוח רעה ruach ra
and you're suffering from depression, I'm the one that's making the decision
to like...
Right, and it's also, right, and it's also
you're not saying "turn off the light, turn off the light".
You know, but you could be, and the pregnant woman could be
saying "I need to eat" or whatever. Right, or I need you
to turn off, right. Yeah, but it's not the same. It's not
the same as this issue, right, it's not as specifically about this
frustrated will.
But anyway, if you take that down,
if he said write it down, yeah, then at least from this
גמרא, right, there would not be a base for it. The גמרא
does not show you that the תרוף הדעת tiruf hada'at is enough
of a concern of a פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh concern for a
דאורייתא. d'Oraita. Okay, let's just finish with the next משנה, Mishnah and
this is where you get the issue of רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
רבי אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. Okay, so our משנה Mishnah. is: רבי אליעזר
אומר בשבת דבריו קיימים מפני שיכול לכתוב אבל לא בחול. Rabbi Eliezer
omer: B'Shabbat d'varav kayamim, mipnei she'yakhol likhtov, aval lo b'chol. So here
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says actually there's a distinction between what is
a verbal קניין kinyan good or not by a שכיב מרע. Fine,
they allowed it on שבת Shabbat because it couldn't—it wasn't an option
of doing
the
קניין. kinyan. Okay, but מפני שיכול לכתוב, mipnei she'yakhol likhtov, now although
you can't be כותב, kotev, you can't do a קניין, kinyan, אבל
לא בחול, aval lo b'chol, they didn't allow it in a weekday.
So
here's the—רבי יהושע אומר: Rabbi Yehoshua omer: בשבת אמרו, B'Shabbat amru, no,
they allowed it on שבת, Shabbat, קל וחומר בחול, kal v'chomer b'chol,
and certainly on a weekday. What does that mean? It means because
on שבת Shabbat you could say we can't make—you know, it's by
שבת Shabbat you say your verbal קניין kinyan counts as a real
קניין, kinyan, so certainly on a weekday you could say שבת Shabbat
all קניינים kinyanim are off the table, right? And because no קניין
kinyan is ever possible. And if nevertheless we allow a verbal קניין
kinyan even in a time when like no קניינים kinyanim are possible,
then certainly we would allow a verbal קניין kinyan to work when
normal קניינים kinyanim can work. Okay, well that's—well, that's what רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says, right? רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it only works
when other things are not an option, it only works on שבת
Shabbat not on חול. chol. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says if
it works when general קניינים kinyanim are off the table, it certainly
works when we're in a normal world of קניינים. kinyanim. Okay, כיוצא
בדבר, k'yotze vadavar, parallel, you could have this question about which way
you go in the following debate:
זכין לקטן ואין זכין לגדול, zakkin l'katan v'ein zakkin l'gadol, דברי רבי
אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says when, you know,
the normal principle: זכין לאדם שלא בפניו, zakkin l'adam shelo b'fanav, I
can take possession of a gift on behalf of somebody else if
they're not around. So he says it only works for a minor,
because a minor is not considered to be like a legal entity
as it were to do it for himself, so therefore they let
me do it for him. But I can't do it for an
adult, let the adult do it for himself. So רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi
Eliezer's basically of the position that they allow these special things only
when the normal options were not available. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
says the reverse. רבי יהושע אומר: Rabbi Yehoshua omer: לקטן אמרו, l'katan
amru, no, no, if they allowed it for a minor even if
the minor can't do it for himself and you're doing it on
behalf of the minor, קל וחומר לגדול, kal v'chomer l'gadol, certainly you
can do it for an adult and you're like his שליח. shaliach.
So then—then certainly you can do it on behalf of him because
then you're seen as an extension of the person himself. Now let
me just say a word about the רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי
אלעזר. Rabbi Elazar. So the question is: is this the same רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who denied the idea of—of a verbal מתנת שכיב
מרע? matnat shechiv mera? So if you read that they're both רבי
אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, which is the riskier גרסא, girsah, then what you're
saying is that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was not as absolute as
we saw in this משנה. Mishnah This משנה Mishnah sounds like he
completely denies a verbal מתנת שכיב מרע. matnat shechiv mera. Here we
see he only denies it on the weekday, he accepts it on
שבת. Shabbat. תוספות proves that this רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer based on
other גמרא, this initial position is categorical. So we have to make
them different. So he therefore says this is רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar
and this is רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. Okay, that there is a
position that categorically denies מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shechiv mera even on
שבת. Shabbat. The last point is the ירושלמי'ס Yerushalmi's גרסא girsah in
our משנה Mishnah that distinguishes between שבת Shabbat and weekdays is not
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer but וחכמים אומרים. v'Chachamim omrim. Okay, but—but anyway,
but the point is the question is: is this a position of
the first position, a categorical, you know, that there's never a מתנת
שכיב מרע, matnat shechiv mera, or is it being qualified in this
משנה that actually it does work on שבת, Shabbat, it just doesn't
work on the weekday. So that's the question: are there two positions
here or three positions. Okay, to be continued tomorrow.